ADAM RULE

Oregon Health & Science University 3181 SW Sam Jackson Park Rd Mail Code: BICC Portland, OR 97239-3098 rulea@ohsu.edu adamrule.com

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Human-Computer Interaction, Human-Centered Data Science, Computational Notebooks, Cognitive Science, Health Informatics, Electronic Health Records

My research focuses on the design and use of data analysis software. I study how analysts currently document and perform their work and aim to make interactive documentation systems that encourage analytic and collaborative best practices.

EDUCATION

2013 - 2018 University of California, San Diego

PHD, Cognitive Science Advisor: Jim Hollan

Committee: Gloria Mark, Brad Voytek, Bill Griswold, Philip Guo, Robert El-Kareh

2011 - 2013 University of Washington, Seattle

MS, Human Centered Design & Engineering

2008 - 2011 University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign

BS, Industrial Engineering — HIGHEST HONORS

AWARDS, HONORS

AWARDS

- 2018 Honorable Mention, CHI 2018 top 5% of all submissions
- 2016 Outstanding Teaching Award, Cognitive Science Department, Winter 2016
- 2012 Honorable Mention, HRI 2012 top 5% of all submissions
- 2012 Microsoft Design Expo Best Presentation

FELLOWSHIPS

- 2019 2021 National Library of Medicine Postdoctoral Training Grant
- 2014 2017 National Library of Medicine Predoctoral Training Grant

CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

- C5 **Adam Rule**, Isaac Goldstein, Michelle Hribar, Michael Chiang. Clinical Documentation as End-User Programming. *In Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems* (CHI), (To Appear) 2020
- Adam Rule, Aurélien Tabard, Jim Hollan. Exploration and Explanation in Computational Notebooks. *In Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)*, 2018 HONORABLE MENTION, TOP 5% OF SUBMISSIONS

Updated Apr 21, 2020 1/5

- C3 Adam Rule, Steven Rick, Michael Chiu, Phillip Rios, Shazia Ashfaq, Alan Calvitti, Wesley Chan, Nadir Weibel, Zia Agha. Validating free-text order entry for a note-centric EHR. In Proceedings of the American Medical Informatics Association Annual Meeting (AMIA), 2015
- C2 Adam Rule, Aurélien Tabard, Karen Boyd, Jim Hollan. Restoring the Context of Interrupted Work with Desktop Thumbnails. *In Proceedings of the Cognitive Science Society Annual Meeting (CogSci)*, 2015
- Adam Rule, Jodi Forlizzi. Designing interfaces for multi-user, multi-robot systems. *In Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Robot Interaction (HRI)*, 2012 HONORABLE MENTION, TOP 5% OF SUBMISSIONS

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- J7 Christine Sinsky, Adam Rule, Genna Cohen, Brian Arndt, Tait Shanafelt, Christopher Sharp, Sally Baxter, Ming Tai-Seale, Sherry Yan, You Chen, Julia Adler-Milstein, Michelle Hribar. Metrics for assessing physician activity using electronic health record log data. *Journal of the American Medical Association (JAMIA)*, (In Press) 2020
- J6 Brad Henriksen, Isaac Goldstein, Adam Rule, Abigail Huang, Haley Dusek, Austin Igelman, Michael Chiang, Michelle Hribar. Electronic Health Records in Ophthalmology: Source and Method of Documentation. American Journal of Ophthalmology, (In Press) 2020
- J5 Adam Rule, Michelle Hribar, Michael Chiang. Using Electronic Health Record Audit Logs to Study Clinical Activity: A Systematic Review of Aims, Measures, and Methods. *Journal of the American Medical Association (JAMIA)*, (In Press) 2020
- J4 Michelle Hribar, Adam Rule, Abigail Huang, Haley Dusek, Isaac Goldstein, Bradley Henriksen, Wei-Chun Lin, Austin Igelman, Michael Chiang. Redundancy of Progress Notes for Serial Office Visits. Ophthalmology, 127(1), 2020
- J3 Adam Rule, Amanda Birmingham, Cristal Zuniga, Ilkay Altintas, Shih-Cheng Huang, Rob Knight, Niema Moshiri, Mai H. Nguyen, Sara Brin Rosenthal, Fernando Pérez, Peter W. Rose. Ten Simple Rules for Writing and Sharing Computational Analyses in Jupyter Notebooks. PLoS Computational Biology, 15(7): e1007007, 2019
- J2 Adam Rule, Ian Drosos, Aurélien Tabard, Jim Hollan. Aiding Collaborative Reuse of Computational Notebooks with Annotated Cell Folding. *Proceedings of the ACM, Human-Computer Interaction*, 1(CSCW), 2018
- J1 Adam Rule, Aurélien Tabard, Jim Hollan. Using Visual Histories to Reconstruct the Mental Context of Suspended Activities. *Human-Computer Interaction*, 32(5-6), 2017

DOCTORAL CONSORTIUM, WORKSHOP & POSTER PUBLICATIONS

- W1 Adam Rule, Aurélien Tabard, Jim Hollan. Traces: A Flexible, Open Source Activity Tracker for Workplace Studies. *Workshop on the Quantified Workplace at the ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW)*, 2017
- P3 **Adam Rule**, Erin Gillespie, Nadir Weibel, Todd Pawlicki. Design Thinking in Radiation Oncology. *Human Factors and Ergonomics Society Healthcare Symposium*, 2016

Updated Apr 21, 2020 2/5

- P2 Adam Rule, Aurélien Tabard, Jim Hollan. Thinking in 4D: Preserving and Sharing Mental Context Across Time. In Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing Companion (CSCW), 2016
- P1 Karen Boyd, **Adam Rule**, Aurélien Tabard, Jim Hollan. Human Values in Tracking and Sharing Computer-Mediated Activity at Work. In Proceedings of the *ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing Companion (CSCW)*, 2016
- D1 Adam Rule. Visualizing Computer Activity to Support the Resumption of Long-term Creative Work. *In Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Creativity & Cognition*, 2015

DISSERTATION

2018 The Design and Use of Computational Notebooks

Adam Rule

Cognitive Science, UC San Diego

MENTORING & ADVISING

2019-Present Oregon Health & Science University

Haley Dusek (MD) Jimmy Chen (MD) Michael Aaby (BS)

2013 - 2018 UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO

Azeem Ghumman (MS Thesis) — Software Engineer @ Zoox Rizwan Ahmad (MS Thesis) — Sr. Software Engineer @ Notebowl Jonas Kemper (MS) — Software Engineer @ McKinsey Dig. Labs Kendall Youngstrom (BS Thesis) — UX Researcher @ Google

Ram Dixit (BS Thesis) — MS Student @ University of Texas, Houston

Karen Boyd (BS) — PhD Student @ University of Maryland Adam Powers (BS) — Information Developer @ Tealium

Regina Cheng (BS) — PhD Student @ University of Washington

Nathan Hassanzadeh (BS)

Katya Noble (BS) — UX Design Intern @ Axos Bank Allison Reiss (BS) — Software Engineer @ Kiran Analytics

Evan Schmitz (BS) — UX Researcher @ Microsoft

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Summer 2019 BMI 510 — Human Computer Interaction in Biomedicine

Mentored Teaching with Michelle Hribar and Michael Chiang, OHSU

Spring 2018 COGS 10 — Cognitive Consequences of Technology

Teaching Assistant with Jim Hollan, UC San Diego

Winter 2017 DSGN 1 — Design of Everyday Things

Teaching Assistant with Jim Hollan, UC San Diego

Updated Apr 21, 2020 3/5

Winter 2016 CSE170/COGS 120 — HCI Design - Outstanding Teaching Award

Teaching Assistant with Scott Klemmer, UC San Diego

HEAD TA OF 8 TEACHING ASSISTANTS

Winter 2015 COGS 102b — Cognitive Ethnography

Teaching Assistant with Melanie McComsey, UC San Diego

Spring 2014 COGS 102c — Cognitive Design Studio

Teaching Assistant with Jim Hollan, UC San Diego

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2019 - Present Oregon Health & Science University

Postdoctoral Scholar

Advisors: Michael Chiang, Michelle Hribar

Researching design and use of electronic health records

2013-2018 University of California San Diego, Design Lab

Research Assistant Advisors: Jim Hollan

Researched design and use of computational notebooks and electronic health records

Summer 2012 Amazon

UX Research Intern

Conducted usability studies of shopping interfaces for clothing and home goods

Summer 2012 PATH

UX Research Intern

Evaluated usability of inventory software for medical equipment

Fall 2011 University of Washington, CHILL Lab

Directed Research Group

Conducted interviews informing design of BabySteps development tracking app

Summer 2011 Carnegie Mellon University, QoLT Center

Research Intern

Conducted research on the design of interfaces for controlling robot teams

Summer 2010 Intel Research

User Research Intern

Conducted research on the design of home assistive robot

SERVICE

Reviewing

CHI (2016,19-20), CSCW (2019), IUI (2019), AMIA (2015-16,19-20), JAMIA (2019-20),

Ophthalmology (2019-20), Applied Clinical Informatics (2019)

OTHER SERVICE

2019 AMIA Student Paper Competition Committee

2019 EXITO Career Panel — Research Diversity program at Portland State University

Updated Apr 21, 2020 4/5

INVITED TALKS

Composition of Clinical Documentation

Oregon Health & Science University, Casey Eye Institute, June 2019

The Design and Use of Computational Notebooks University of Washington, Interactive Data Lab, Dec 2018 Oregon Health & Science University, Medical Informatics, Nov 2018

Field Methods in Human Computer Interaction Guest Lecture, COGS 13 (Field Methods) UC San Diego, May 2018

Exploration and Explanation in Computational Notebooks *UC Berkeley, Data Science Institute,* Dec 2017

Cognitive Science & Design

Guest Lecture, COGS 1 (Intro to Cognitive Science) UC San Diego, Nov 2016

Guest Lecture, COGS 1 (Intro to Cognitive Science) UC San Diego, Oct 2015

Updated Apr 21, 2020 5/5